Hello, and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today
we're going to be looking at the
hydrolysis of triacylglycerides.
So, in this particular reaction, what
we're going to be looking at is a
triacylglyceride just like the structure
here that has already been formed.
So, with these, they can
be broken down, right?
If you were to be eating a fat or
oil, what is your body doing to digest
that when it goes through metabolism?
It's going to have to break it
down into its basic components.
So the first step of how that happens in
your body is it goes through hydrolysis.
So triacylglycerols are
hydrolyzed, meaning that
they're split by water, right?
We're going to take our little water
scissors, and we're going to cut
where it is most vulnerable, which
is right here where the ester bond
is in each of these structures.
Right.
So we're going to cut at the ester.
Now, in order for this to happen,
think about your stomach conditions.
What's your stomach like, right?
It's very acidic.
There's a lot of enzymes down
there to help break it apart.
So it needs to be in this
presence of a strong acid.
Think your stomach.
It's very acidic.
Now, without the presence of enzymes,
your body wouldn't function very well.
So we're going to also say there can be
digestive enzymes to help break that down.
And being that we're talking
about lipids, The enzyme that's
going to be used is lipase, right?
So lipase, ace means enzyme.
Um, so that's what
we're going to be doing.
And you can see that lip part or lipids.
If I were to give you this
breakdown here, what we're going
to follow is the following formula.
We have a triacylglycerol or a fat.
It's going to be reacting
with three waters.
Being that this triacylglycerol
has three prongs on it, right?
So it has a three little tentacles.
Each one gets cut with a water.
Now, this has to be in the presence
of an acid to make it possible.
And when that does, it's going
to break it down into three
fatty acids and a glycerol.
If I have the following, right, I have
a glycerol tripalim mal palimitate here.
So if we're going to cut
that, where would we do that?
Well, if we were to look here,
where is it most vulnerable?
So if you can see with, by me
highlighting, We have the following
ester area on each of these structures.
So this is where those two
electronegative groups are going
to be pulling at the bonds.
So the oxygens are pulling
in both directions.
So with that being said, it's going
to cut at each of these little parts.
So if we add our little scissors
here, and we are to cut.
We are going to be doing that
with the addition of water.
Okay, so we're adding
water to each of these.
Now, if you can remember,
how does hydrolysis occur?
Well, being that you're using
water, you're adding an H to one
part and OH to the other, right?
Those are your two p your
two parts of your scissors.
With that, what we are going to
do is we're going to cut this.
We're going to take our structure,
so let's copy this and move it down,
and we are going to just separate.
Now, if I do that like so, right,
that is separate into our two parts.
Let's erase the purple highlighting.
I'm going to erase our little scissors.
And what were our pieces that
we were cutting from before?
Well, we're adding H and OH.
So you got to think, what were
your functional groups, right?
In the condensation or the formation
of these, you have an, you have
a carboxylic acid on one side,
or the fatty acid on the right.
And we have the glycerol on the left,
which had all the different OHs.
So we are going to add the Hs on
the left and the OHs on the right.
All right, so these are our
different parts of our final
products in this reaction.
So when we go through this, that
glycerol tripalimutate splits into,
um, if we want to try to write the
whole thing, we have palmitic acid on
one part, And then we have glycerol on
the other as our different fragments.
And that's the idea, hydrolysis,
you just add acid, and that's
how we break it down in our body.
I hope that this video helped you, so
thank you so much for watching, please
hit that like and subscribe button, I hope
to see you back for future introductory
biochemistry and organic videos.
Have a great day, bye now!